Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף Daf is ס"ג Samech Gimmel
63, and we pick up at the bottom of ס"ב עמוד ב,
Samech Bais Amud Bais, and we've been talking about the debate in
the גמרא, Gemara, the issue that got us started was it was
an issue in the משנה Mishna whether a non-Jewish house in a
חצר Chatzer created a problem or not. And according to a רבי
אליעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov, it was only if there
were two Jews in the חצר; Chatzer; one is not a problem.
And the גמרא Gemara says we rule like him, and that led
to an issue about can a תלמיד Talmid rule this way במקום
רב, B'makom Rav, since it's such an obvious פסק, Psak, it's not
a problem. And the גמרא Gemara seems to be saying no matter
how obvious the פסק Psak is, even in an egg in milk,
a תלמיד Talmid cannot פסקן Pasken במקום רב. B'makom Rav. Although I
did mention to you תוספות Tosafos introduces some qualifications: one is if
somebody is asking if something is אסור Assur and you know it's
אסור, Assur, you need to tell them. The גמרא Gemara will talk
about אפרושי מאיסורא Afrushe Mei'issura or stopping an איסור, Issur, but תוספות
Tosafos seems to feel that even if it's a שאלה Shaila and
the answer is אסור, Assur, that's in the category of stopping somebody
from doing an איסור. Issur. And number two is תוספות Tosafos says
you can talk about it theoretically, just not give an actual practical
פסק Psak to a practical question. And the third and maybe the
most important is although that the גמרא Gemara emphasizes oh, you can't
even פסקן Pasken something that's written in מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit or
an egg in milk, תוספות Tosafos says that all of those are
cases where there actually is a חידוש Chiddush and the answer is
not obvious. But if the answer actually is obvious and does not
really require judgment and weighing, then actually it is not a problem,
although it's a little bit against...
Is that רב חסדא Rav Chisda like my favorite?
Yes. So if you take a look at let's read that actually,
four lines from the bottom of תוספות Tosafos and then when we
get a little bit more in, I'll even tell you about some
of the הלכות Halachos about this. But four lines from the bottom
of the big תוספות Tosafos on ס"ב עמוד ב, Samech Bais Amud
Bais, ואמר רב חסדא. V'omar Rav Chisda. רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, four
lines, it says ואמר ר"י. V'omar Ri. ואמר ר"י דדווקא בדבר שנראה
חידוש לשואל. V'omar Ri d'davka b'davar shenirei chiddush l'shoel.
So maybe one issue, number one, is how much judgment it requires
on your part. But number two is maybe it's how much it's
perceived of as being a חידוש. Chiddush. Oh, he פסקנ'ד Pasken'd so
and so, you know. So now why should that matter? ואפילו ביעתא
בכותחא ומגילת תענית בהאי גוונא איירי. V'afillu beita b'chutcha u'megillat taanit b'hai
gavna airy. So even though מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit is all written,
not everybody knows what's written down, for some people if you פסקן
Pasken a שולחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, it's a חידוש, Chiddush, they don't
know the שולחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, they don't know that law. So
now why should that matter if it's not a real הוראה, Hora'ah,
if it's an obvious point? Because what is the issue of פסקנ'ינג
Paskening במקום רב? B'makom Rav? So for תוספות Tosafos and it will
become clear in the גמרא, Gemara, the issue has to do with
כבוד הרב, Kavod Harav, that to show respect for your רבי, Rebbe,
you don't assume authority in his presence. Okay, so that has a
lot to do not just with reality but with perception. If it's
perceived like you are assuming authority, like oh look, his רבי Rebbe
was right there and he gave me this big חידוש, Chiddush, you
know,
that you say אמן Amen after אל יחרינו. Al Yachreinu. Okay, so
I didn't know that, whatever. So frame it as a big חידוש.
Chiddush. So it's perceived of that you פסקן Pasken במקום רב B'makom
Rav and you somewhat usurped or infringed upon his authority. So perception
according to תוספות Tosafos is a big part of it.
Wait one minute, wait one minute. Okay, fine. He says ולא נקטינו
אלא לאשמועינן דאפילו בהני שהתלמיד בעצמו יודע שאינו טועה. V'lo naktinu ela
l'ashmi'inan d'afillu b'hanei shehatalmid be'atzmo yodea she'ino toeh. Even in something that
to you is black and white and there's really, you think it's
not even a judgment call, okay, אסור להורות Assur l'horos if the
person perceives it as a חידוש. Chiddush. What?
Isn't that דעת תורה? Daas Torah?
No, no, no, not you know your רבי Rebbe is saying something
wrong. That's the idea of אפרושי מאיסורא Afrushe Mei'issura we're going to
get to something like that. No, no, it means your רבי Rebbe
is just present, somebody asks me a שאלה, Shaila, my רבי Rebbe
is present, I know it's not even a שאלה, Shaila, I know
it's black and white, I have no question that what I'm saying
is right, but this person perceives it as a שאלה Shaila and
perceives what I'm going to say as a חידוש. Chiddush. So therefore
because of the perception aspect, that's an issue of respect for my
רבי. Rebbe. It looks like I am assuming authority in my
רבי'ס Rebbe's
presence, not contradicting him.
Isn't that כבוד התורה? Kavod Hatorah?
It is not דעת תורה, Daas Torah, it's כבוד הרב. Kavod Harav.
Anyway let me read a little more. אבל דבר שהשואל יודע שידוע
מנהגו של דבר. Aval davar shehashoel yodea sheyadu'a minhago shel davar.
But something that even the asker knows, he basically knows this, כגון
נותן טעם לפגם. k'gon nosein taam lifgam.
Interesting example, right? Like okay I cooked with a
pot, it was I hadn't used it for three days ago, it's
fine, נותן טעם לפגם, nosein taam lifgam, whatever. So something like that
where maybe some people ask anyway to just because people are anxious
and they need to ask, but they really know what the הלכה
Halacha is and it's not a חידוש Chiddush when you פסקן Pasken
it for them, כשמורה לו היתר אין זה קרוי דבר חידוש. keshomoreh
lo heter ein zeh karui davar chiddush. Yeah,
of course, okay fine, it was obvious, yeah, that is שרי. sharrei.
Okay so anyway and we'll hold off the last line for a
minute because it's what we're about to read, but the importance about
that is that it's on the one hand, you know, saying it's
not true you can't rule anything. Things that are obvious you can
rule, but it's also with an emphasis about the issue about perception
because it is about respect for the רב Rav in the רב'ס
Rav's presence. So let's hear a little bit more about that and
the next line in the גמרא Gemara is really going to focus
on this issue about sort of, you know, respect and the assuming
authority. Okay. So now the last line of ס"ג ע"ב *Samech-Gimel Amud-Bet*,
oh, I forgot to mention ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh. *Rosh Chodesh*. Okay,
so last line of ס"ג ע"ב *Samech-Gimel Amud-Bet*, רב rav חסדא *Rav
Chisda* אורי *orei* בכפרי *be'Kafri*, רב rav חסדא *Rav Chisda* פסקן pasken.
*pasken* in כפרי *Kafri* בשני דרב הונא *be'shnei de'Rav Huna* in the
years of רב rav הונא *Rav Huna* when רב rav, הונא *Rav
Huna* was still alive, his רבי Rebbe *Rebbi*, and כפרי *Kafri* now
they were both in בבל *Bavel* but כפרי *Kafri* was a different
city. So here's also the question of what does it mean in
the presence of your רב rav *Rav*? Is he in the room?
Is he in the same city? So here he was in a
different city. רב rav המנונא *Rav Hamnuna* אורי *orei* now רב rav?
המנונא *Rav Hamnuna* פסקן pasken *pasken* top of ס"ג ע"א *Samech-Gimel Amud-Aleph*
בחרסא דאגמי *be'Charsa de'Arga* in this city called חרסא דאגמי *Charsa de'Arga*
בשני דרב חסדא *be'shnei de'Rav Chisda* when רב Rav חסדא *Rav Chisda*
was still alive. So basically, you know, what רב Rav חסדא *Rav
Chisda* did to his רבי rebbe *Rebbi*, רב Rav המנונא *Rav Hamnuna*
did to רב חסדא *Rav Chisda*. So it all comes back to
you. Okay. רבינא Ravina *Ravina* now so now presumably that that the
point being that if you're in a different city it's okay but
we're going to come back to that in a moment. רבינא Ravina
סר סכינא בבבל *Ravina sar skina be'Bavel*. רבינא Ravina, *Ravina* inspected knives
in בבל *Bavel*. Now what this is is this really shows that
this is well when his רבי rebbe *Rebbi* was around, when רב
אשי Rav Ashi *Rav Ashi* was still alive and living in בבל
*Bavel*, not in the same city but in the same country. Now
what this this really shows the point about the idea of כבוד
kavod *Kavod* because it's not a פסק psak, *psak* issue meaning whenever
a new Rabbi would come to a city they would basically the
שוחטים *shochtim* would show him the knife and he would do a,
you know, a whole inspection of the knife. And the purpose of
it was not really to פסקן pasken *pasken*, you know, but it
was to show like to as a demonstration that you are the
rabbinic authority of the location and the way we demonstrate it, we
the שוחטים *shochtim*, you know, is by showing you the knife to
show ultimately you're the one that is overseeing, you know, the כשרות
*kashrut* of the city. So it was really a symbolic gesture that
demonstrated who's you know who's the and sometimes actually it was a
real שאלה shaylah. *shaila* and he needed to look at the knife.
But anyway, here because of this emphasis it really seems that this
is the idea, that you do this thing and and your רבי
rebbe *Rebbi* is around, it shows that you're assuming the authority. So
אמר ליה Amar lei, רב אשי *amar leh Rav Ashi* now again
he was not in the same city but he just was in
the same country. In בבל *Bavel*
though. I understand, same country, not same city. So אמר ליה Amar
lei רב אשי *amar leh Rav Ashi*, so רב אשי *Rav Ashi*
said to him, מאי טעמא עביד מר הכי *mai ta'ama avid mar
hachi*? Why is are you doing this? מר *Mar*, like a respect,
well not but anyway it was his student. Why are you doing
this? I'm still around. So אמר ליה Amar lei *amar leh*, why
shouldn't I be able to do this? והא רב המנונא אורי בחרסא
דאגמי בשני דרב חסדא *ve'ha Rav Hamnuna orei be'Charsa de'Arga be'shnei de'Rav
Chisda*. רב המנונא *Rav Hamnuna* ruled in a חרסא דאגמי *Charsa de'Arga*
in a different city when רב חסדא *Rav Chisda* was around, when
he was still alive. אמר ליה Amar lei *amar leh*, no, לאו
אורי איתמר *lav orei itmar*. You got the story wrong. It was
the version is he didn't teach, he didn't פסקן pasken *pasken*. Your
version of it was he פסקן pasken *pasken*, my version of that
story is he didn't פסקן pasken *pasken*. So אמר ליה Amar lei
*amar leh*, so he said back to him, איתמר אורי ואיתמר לאו
אורי *itmar orei ve'itmar lav orei*. No, there are two versions of
the story. One is he פסקן pasken *pasken*, the other is he
didn't פסקן pasken *pasken*. בשני דרב הונא רבהו דלאו אורי *be'shnei de'Rav
Huna rabehu de'lav orei* and they're both right. When רב הונא *Rav
Huna* was still alive he he wouldn't פסקן pasken *pasken* even in
another city. ואורי בשני דרב חסדא *ve'orei be'shnei de'Rav Chisda*, he did
פסקן pasken *pasken* when רב חסדא *Rav Chisda* was alive after רב
הונא *Rav Huna* had passed. Why? דתלמיד חבר דיליה הוה *de'talmid chaver
dilei hava*. He wasn't fully a student, he was a student-colleague. Okay,
so yes he was he was younger, he studied under him, but
then when he became, you know, came into his own he became
a colleague who had, you know, a student a student-colleague not a
full student. And therefore as a student-colleague he had more latitude. There
wasn't this issue that he was not in in a position to
assume authority. Now, does that mean he could do it literally in
a presence, in the same city? Maybe not, but at least in
a different city, even in the same country, that was a that
was allowed. And then he said, ואנא נמי תלמיד talmid חבר דמר
אנא *ve'ana nami talmid chaver de'mar ana*. And I am also your
student-colleague. So since we are also like, you know, it's not a
full רב תלמיד talmid, *Rav talmid* relationship, therefore I should have the
latitude to do this at least if I'm in another city. Yes,
רבקה *Rivka*.
What exactly does סר סכינא *sar skina*?
It means inspected the knives.
Which means like what?
Yeah, he just tells
inspected the knives of all the
of the שוחטים *shochtim*, yeah, or a שוחט *shochet* brought it to
him to inspect. And the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says and this is
what the last line in תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says is, the גמרא
Gemara, *Gemara* says לא אמרו Amru: להראות סכין לחכם אלא מפני כבודו
של חכם *lo amru le'harot sakin le'chacham ela mipnei kvodo shel chacham*.
That it wasn't really a פסק psak, *psak* שאלה shaylah *shaila*, right.
It was really a matter of authority.
Exactly. That's exactly the point. It is symbolic to demonstrate who is
the rabbinic authority, who's the boss. Right, who is the rabbinic authority
of the town. Exactly, and that's why it was an issue because
this is about not a question is the תלמיד talmid, *talmid* making
a mistake, right, the idea of in the presence of the רב
*Rav* is an issue about demonstrating like assuming authority when, you know,
when the real authority is there's a greater authority that is around.
Now, maybe I'll stop here because I see people are getting a
little bit upset about this and just to mention, I mean I
was going to I was going to mention this later, but I'll
just mention that this is really here I'll just read you a
line from the שלחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch *Shulchan Aruch*, this actually occurs
in the שלחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch *Shulchan Aruch* in יורה דעה *Yoreh
De'ah* under הלכות halachot כבוד kavod רב *Hilchot Kavod Rav*. That's where
these occur. So if there was any question about what this is
about, it's under כבוד רבו *Kavod Rabbo*. And here for example I'll
read other parts about this but here it says like this, it
says ואסור לאדם להורות לפני
רבו *ve'asur le'adam le'horot lifnei rabbo*. And then it says, ואסור לאדם
להורות לפני רבו *ve'asur le'adam le'horot lifnei rabbo*.
What, yeah.
One minute. It says like this. Here, אבל
לקבוע
עצמו להוראה לשבת להורות אפילו בסוף העולם אסור להורות עד שימות רבו
או עד שיתן לו רשות. o ad sheyiten lo reshut. So you
can be given a רשות. reshut. I authorize you to פסקן. pasken
It’s okay. You can פסקן pasken even and that is, thank you,
yes. And that is so a lot of what halachically סמיכה smicha
means nowadays. סמיכה smicha nowadays is not the סמיכה smicha in the
גמרא. Gemara. And the really סמיכה smicha has two functions. One is
it has a sort of social function, a societal function which it
basically just tells people this guy knows his stuff and you can
trust him to פסקן pasken and it’s basically a form of licensing.
Okay, but halachically the function that סמיכה smicha has is it’s a
רשות הוראה במקום רבו. reshut horaah bemakom rabo. You’re my student, you
studied under me, I say יורה יורה, yoreh yoreh, I am giving
you permission to פסקן pasken even in my presence. Now, what does
my presence mean? Physically in my presence? In the same city? Not
in my presence? In a different city? Fine, we can discuss that.
But the basic point is that is a היתר הוראה heter horaah
where the halachic function of that is במקום רבו. bemakom rabo. And
that is, so that’s not spelled out here in the גמרא, Gemara?
okay, but that is the הלכה halacha that if the רב gives
permission, it’s allowed. But without that permission, it is seen as usurping
or compromising the רב’s authority. All right, now let’s see as it
continues. Yes, Charlie?
Yeah, so I’m surprised that this comes up with רבינא Ravina and
רב אשי because they disagree with each other right all through ש"ס.
Shas.
Right, so oh you mean how are you allowed to disagree? Because
you’re not allowed to be חולק על רבו? cholek al rabo? Okay,
so first of all, as תוספות Tosafot says, we’re talking about practical
פסק, psak, although this idea of inspecting knives is a practical פסק,
poskened but the area that it is a problem, certainly the realm
of תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah where we can debate things, you know,
anything under the sun and that’s not being compromised by this. Doesn’t
matter רב or תלמיד or whatever, you know, you debate. That’s תוספות’s
Tosafot point about theoretical. It’s specific acts that demonstrate sort of who’s
the halachic authority here. So that’s either פסקן-ing pasken of a practical
issue or it is this issue of inspecting the knives which is
a very symbolic act that demonstrated who is the halachic authority. I
will read you though a line since you raised that issue about
arguing with your רב, you know, because another הלכה halacha is that
it’s אסור לחלוק על רבו. assur lachlok al rabo. Like this isn’t
even being חולק, cholek, this is just פסקן-ing. pasken You might פסקן
pasken the exact same way. But how about לחלוק על רבו? lachlok
al rabo? How does that factor into the frame of תלמוד תורה,
Talmud Torah, right? So here I’ll just read you a lines from
the פתחי תשובה. Pitchei Teshuva. It says, like he says like this
in סימן רמ"ב. siman resh-mem-bet. He says,
one minute,
so the רמ"א Rema says, אבל מותר לחלוק עליו באיזה פסק או
הוראה אם יש לו ראיות והוכחות לדבריו שהדין עמו. aval mutar lachlok
alav beeizeh psak o horaah im yesh lo reayot vehokhachot ledvarav shehadin
imo. So first of all, you can even be חולק cholek on
him with a פסק, posken you know, not necessarily you פסקן-ing pasken
to other, again, this gets to the next question of פסקן-ing in
his presence. But anyway, if you actually can bring evidence. And the
פתחי תשובה Pitchei Teshuva says, he says like
this: עיין בתשובת חוט השני שגדול אחד התרעם עליו על השגתו על
גדולי הקדמונים
ומה גם למה שהשתמט מדברי ש"ס ופוסקים.
ayen betshuvat chut hashani shegadol echad hitraem alav al hasagato
al gedolei hakadmonim uma gam lama shehishtamet midivrei shas uposkim. So somebody
once complained to the author of his תשובת חוט השני Tshuvat Chut
HaShani says, "How could you have a different opinion than the great
פוסקים poskim that preceded you?" And what's worse than that is that
when you were sort of disagreeing with them, you say, "Oh, they
must have missed the following גמרא." Gemara How dare you say they
missed a גמרא? Gemara, Okay. And anyway, and then it says: והשיב
לו שאין על זה להתרעם כי כן מצינו במחברים שכל דור ודור
לא נמנעו להשיג על גדולים שלפניהם. veheshiv lo sheein al zeh lehitraem
ki ken matzinu bamechabrim shekol dor vador lo nimnu lehasig al gedolim
shelifneihem. And every generation always, you know, that’s all nature of תורה
שבעל פה. Torah shebe'al peh. You argue. You argue on the previous
generation and each and actually it’s a sign of respect to say
he might have overlooked the following thing, rather than saying he got
it wrong and so on. Anyway, but that issue of how does
this play out vis-a-vis the whole idea of the free-for-all of תורה
שבעל פה Torah shebe'al peh is definitely, you know, they work to
delineate those lines. But that's actually even an issue of disagreeing. Here
it’s not even disagreeing, just פסקן-ing and assuming authority. But again, להלכה
lehalacha that's what היתר הוראה heter horaah is about and that's what
the halachic function of סמיכה. smicha. Yes? One of the things is,
one is
I'm just thinking about
סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, דיני נפשות dinei nefashot versus דיני ממונות, dinei mamonot, let's
say, right? Because דיני ממונות dinei mamonot it didn't make a difference
to start from the bigger one because you were allowed to disagree,
but דיני נפשות dinei nefashot they didn't want, they didn't want... They
started from the lesser people, they didn't want you to disagree. So
you know, so I’m not sure how that fits in here. That’s
one. Yeah, I don't want to get into that. That's whatever. But
let's say it's not even your רב but the recognized גדול. gadol.
Right, right. So that’s the issue. How much of this is about
רב מובהק, rav muvhak, not רב מובהק? rav muvhak? How much is
it that somebody is identified as the, as you say, like the
רב of everyone even though not my personal רב? So that is
discussed להלכה. lehalacha. Okay, let's take a look as it continues.
רבינא איקלע למחוזא. Ravina ikla leMechuza. רבינא Ravina dropped by in מחוזא.
Mechuza. אייתו אושפיזכניה סכינא. Aitu ushpizkaneih sakina. So his host brought him
a knife to inspect. So he was going to go שחט shacht
for him a nice calf or whatever to feed to רבינא, Ravina
so the innkeeper showed him a nice before he went and שחט
shachted it, וכמחווי ליה v'kamachvei lei and he inspected it. אמר ליה,
Amar lei
I'm sorry, וכמחווי ליה v'kamachvei lei and he brought it to him,
he showed it to him, he brought him a knife and he
showed it to him. אמר ליה amar lei, so רבינא said to
him, זיל אמטיה לרבא. zil amteih l'Rava. Go bring it to רבא,
Rava, you know, this is מחוזא, Mechuza, מחוזא Mechuza is רבא's Rava
city as we know, רבא Rava was the רבא Rava of מחוזא.
Mechuza. I can't I can't inspect the knife, it's רבא's Rava city.
אמר amar ליה he said to him, לא סבר מר הדאמר רבא?
lo savar Mar had'amar Rava? I'm sorry, I skipped a line. I
skipped the key line that introduced it. Okay, so אמר רבא, amar
Rava, excuse me, back before that, before that, about ten lines from
the top, I'm sorry I skipped that. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, back
to where there's a little circle with a line in it. I'm
going back. צורבא מרבנן חזי לנפשיה. Tzurba me'rabanan chazi l'nafshei. Although you're
not allowed to inspect a knife for somebody else, if you're a
תלמיד חכם talmid chacham and צורבא מרבנן tzurba me'rabanan means you're even
you're still a תלמיד, you're a student, nevertheless you're allowed to inspect
your own knife if you want to שחט shacht your own meat,
okay, because that's not like an a symbolic act of who's the
boss, that's just dealing with your own שאלות, shailos, which is allowed.
Okay, so רבינא איקלע למיחוזא, ikla l'Mechuza, now רבינא came to מחוזא,
Mechuza, אייתו אושפיזכניה סכינא, aiti ushpizchanei sakina, so the innkeeper brought him
a knife, וכמחווי ליה v'kamachvei lei and showed it to him. אמר
ליה זיל אמטיה לרבא, zil amteih l'Rava, go show רבא Rava because
מחוזא Mechuza is רבא's Rava city. אמר ליה he said to him,
לא סבר מר הדאמר רבא צורבא מרבנן חזי לנפשיה? lo savar Mar
had'amar Rava tzurba me'rabanan chazi l'nafshei? Wait a minute, רבא Rava himself
פסק poskening that a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, even a תלמיד, can
פסק poskening for himself, can look at the knife himself. אמר ליה
אמר ליה, אנא מזבן זבינא. ana mizban zavina. I'm sorry, I'm going
to be buying the meat from you. So at this stage it's
not yet my meat. Okay, so if maybe I maybe pre-paid for
it, I don't know exactly. But at this stage you're שחט, shechting,
it's your meat, you're going to sell it, so therefore I'm taking
this act of authority and פסק posken or not even פסק poskening
just inspecting the knife of someone else, because then afterwards I'll buy
it, but right now it is not it is not my own
meat. רבי אלעזר מגרוניא ורב אבא בר תחליפא, Rabbi Eliezer mi-Gronya v'Rav
Abba bar Tachlifa, so רבי אלעזר מגרוניא ורב אבא בר תחליפא Rabbi
Eliezer mi-Gronya v'Rav Abba bar Tachlifa איקלעו לבי רב אחא בריה דרב
איקא. iklu l'bei Rav Acha brei d'Rav Ika. They came to the
house of רב אחא בריה דרב איקא, Rav Acha brei d'Rav Ika,
באתריה דרב אחא בר יעקב, b'asrei d'Rav Acha bar Yaakov, and it
was the locale of רב אחא בר יעקב Rav Acha bar Yaakov
where רב אחא בר יעקב Rav Acha bar Yaakov was the הלכה
halachic authority. A different רב אחא Rav Acha than the one whose
house they were in. בעי רב אחא בריה דרב איקא למיעבד להו
עגלא תילתא, Ba'ei Rav Acha brei d'Rav Ika l'meivad lehu igla tilsa,
so the host, this רב אחא בריה דרב איקא Rav Acha brei
d'Rav Ika wanted to make them a nice fatty calf. עגלא תילתא,
Igla tilsa, רש"י Rashi has two versions whether it means three years
old or the third or right a third of its growth or
the third one that was born from the mother, anyway this nice
delicious calf.
אייתו סכינא וכמחווי להו. Aiti sakina v'kamachvei lehu. So he brought a
knife and he showed his two visiting rabbis, he said I could
you check my knife before I go שחט. shacht. אמר להו רב
אבא
בר תחליפא, Amar lehu Rav Abba bar Tachlifa, so רב אבא בר
תחליפא Rav Abba bar Tachlifa who was one of the two visiting
rabbis said to the other two of them, לא לחוש ליה לסבא?
lo lachush lei l'saba?
So aren't you aren't you know aren't you being shouldn't you be
concerned for the elder, for the רב אחא בר יעקב Rav Acha
bar Yaakov whose city this is? So you know who's the authority
here? How can you be showing this to us? אמר להו רבי
אלעזר מגרוניא, Amar lehu Rabbi Eliezer mi-Gronya, so the other visiting rabbi
רבי אלעזר מגרוניא Rabbi Eliezer mi-Gronya said, no no no that's not
a problem. הכי אמר רבא, Hachi amar Rava, רבא Rava says צורבא
מרבנן חזי לנפשיה, tzurba me'rabanan chazi l'nafshei, so a you
know תלמיד חכם talmid chacham can inspect for himself.
Why is he showing it to you? What? No we didn't need
to show it to...
okay so he didn't need to show it, or maybe he could
show it to them because maybe they were more in a position
to judge than he is, but it's okay for them to פסק
posken because it's for themselves, they're going to be eating the meat,
and they visit a סעודה se'ul... he's hosting them. וחזי ואיענש. Chazi
v'ianash. So they inspected the knife and then ואיענש רבי אלעזר מגרוניא.
v'ianash Rabbi Eliezer mi-Gronya. רבי אלעזר מגרוניא Rabbi Eliezer mi-Gronya who was
the one that said it's okay you can go ahead and do
it, he was punished. Okay somehow something bad befell him and it
was seen to be as a punishment for for going ahead and
looking at the knife. So the גמרא Gemara says how could this
be? והאמר רבא צורבא מרבנן חזי לנפשיה, Ve'amar Rava tzurba me'rabanan chazi
l'nafshei, that a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham can inspect for himself? No,
שאני התם דאתחילו בכבודה. shani hasam d'atchilu bichvoda. There it's different because
they already opened up saying oh we should show it to the
רב of the city. So when you actually introduce that, what you
show to the רב say nah don't bother, that's a sign of
disrespect. If you hadn't said anything we'd be fine. But once you
introduced it and then dismissing it that's a lack of
respect. ואיבעית אימא, Ve'iba'it eima, if you want it's different and this
gets to Michael's point. שאני רב אחא בר יעקב דמופלג. Shani Rav
Acha bar Yaakov d'muflyag. רב אחא בר יעקב Rav Acha bar Yaakov
was different because he was he because he was מופלג, muflyag, which
could mean he was like so רש"י Rashi says היה הרבה מאד
היה זקן וחכם, haya harbei me'od haya zaken v'chacham, מופלג muflyag could
mean like you know could mean very old it could also mean
very wise. Or both. Anyway so he was you know a big
he was a גדול. gadol. So for him maybe the laws are
different even for yourself you need to show it to someone else.
Now by the way there's an interesting issue since I've been reading
from שלחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch about what does it mean פסק psak
for yourself? You know, I mean I mean you know ninety percent
of the time any you know people that are you know that
know הלכה halacha פסק psak for themselves like oh my gosh I
forgot יעלה ויבא Ya'aleh v'Yavo it's ראש חודש. Okay I got to
daven שחרית Shacharis but I don't have to say it again. Oh
שחרית... Shacharis... I have to say it again. So oh you just
פסקנד paskened. *paskened* for yourself! You know? So so you're you know
well so a lot of times you're פסקנינג *paskening* for yourself so
you know is that really an issue that even counts as פסקן
*pasken* or whatever anyway so the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch *Shulchan Aruch*
says here he says
one minute אם בני ביתו של כמה הוצטרכו להוראה ושאלו לא יורה
להם
במקום רבו bimkom rabbo *im
b'nei beiso shel komet hutztarchu l'horah u'sh'alo lo yoreh lahem b'makom rabo*.
I can't even answer questions from you know
that my spouse or my kids ask me. Okay and then
so that's debate that is seriously debated by later פוסקים poskim. *poskim*
who say do me a break that's considered פסקנינג *paskening* for yourself
you know but that's the question at what stage are you taking
a role of authority and what stage are you just like you
know managing your own הלכה halacha *halachic* life?
All right fine now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ורב אחא בר
יעקב *v'Rav Acha bar Yaakov* I'm sorry we just did אמר רבא
Amar Rava: *amar Rava* says רבא Rava *Rava* לאפרושי מאיסורא אפילו בפני
רבו bifnei rabbo. שפיר דמי *l'afroshe m'issura afilu bifne rabo shafir dami*
to stop somebody from doing an איסור *issur* you can do that
even if your רבי rebbe, *Rebbe* is around and your רבי rebbe,
*Rebbe* isn't acting you
can
act to stop somebody from doing an איסור *issur*. Now תוספות Tosafot
*Tosafos* included in that if somebody asks me can I do something
and the answer is אסור *assur* I'm allowed to say even if
maybe it's not obvious that they're about to act even if I
postpone you know say ah I can't פסקן *pasken* go ask somebody
else. Okay תוספות Tosafot, *Tosafos* says if the answer is אסור *assur*
that's אפרושי מאיסורא *afroshe m'issura* and I have to tell him it's
אסור *assur*. Now רבינא הוה יתיב קמיה דרב אשי *Ravina hava yosiv
kamei d'Rav Ashi*. רבינא *Ravina* was sitting in front of רב אשי
*Rav Ashi*. חזייה לההוא גברא *chazaya l'hu gavra* he saw a certain
person דקא אסר ליה לחמריה בצינצא בשבת *d'ka'atzar leh l'chamrei b'tzintza b'Shabbos*.
He was tying up his donkey to a tree to a palm
tree on שבת *Shabbos*. You're not allowed to use מחובר *mechubar*. רמא
ביה קלא *rama bei kaley* ולא אקבי *v'lo akbei*. He yelled at
him he said said stop! He didn't pay any attention. אמר ליה
*amar leh* he said ליהוי האי גברא בשמתא *lehavyei hai gavra b'shamsa*
you should put be put in נידוי *nidui* put in חרם *cherem*.
אמר ליה *amar leh* then he turned and he said כי האי
גוונא מי חזי כאפיקורסות *ki hai gavna mi chazai k'apikorsus*. So if
you remember רב אשי *Rav Ashi* gave רבינא *Ravina* a hard time
for looking at knives right at the top of the דף *daf*.
So then he turned to רב אשי *Rav Ashi* and he said
is this considered like אפיקורסות *apikorsus* אפיקורסות *apikorsus*? Now אפיקורס *apikorus* which
we say is means like heresy actually when the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*
בסנהדרין *b'Sanhedrin* describes what the word אפיקורס *apikorus* means in the famous
משנה *Mishnah* of those who don't have a חלק לעולם הבא *chelek
l'olam haba* says it is someone that is מבזה חבירו בפני תלמיד
חכם *m'vazeh chaveiro bifne talmid chacham* or מבזה תלמיד חכם *m'vazeh talmid
chacham*. Understands it very much as a way of showing of like
disrespect for authority or you know more than disrespect you know what's
a more what's a more word than disrespect anyway not it's more
than disrespect it's like a
flagrant defaming but anyway anyway it's you know it's spitting in the
face of authority. So anyway so he said is this considered to
be that because here I am not only did I tell him
stop which maybe is clearly in the אפרושי מאיסורא *afroshe m'issura* category
but I put him in חרם *cherem*. Putting in חרם *cherem* is
an act of rabbinic authority and I did that in your presence
would this be an issue of תלמיד במקום רבו bimkom rabbo *talmid
b'makom rabo*? We saw at the beginning that he considered himself a
תלמיד חבר *talmid chaver* but anyway he wanted to have he turned
to him and said what's what's the story is this a problem?
אמר ליה *amar leh* אין חכמה ואין תבונה ואין עצה לנגד ה׳
*ein chochma v'ein tevuna v'ein eitzah l'neged Hashem*. There's no wisdom and
you know understanding in the presence of God. כל מקום שיש בו
חילול ה׳ *kol makom sheyeish bo chillul Hashem* wherever there's a desecration
to God אין חולקין כבוד לרב *ein cholkin kavod l'rav* you do
not worry about כבוד הרב *kavod ha'rav*. So this would be an
appropriate thing. Now I think the important point about this is as
I said it's going further than the idea of אפרושי מאיסורא *afroshe
m'issura*. Sometimes the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does quote this idea אין חכמה
ואין תבונה *ein chochma v'ein tevuna* when it comes to stopping somebody
from doing an איסור *issur*. But here it seems like he wasn't
going to stop him. The guy was ignoring him but you still
had to defend God's honor. So to have let this act go
without acting on it I mean this is how it was perceived
of in that society okay that that to have let this act
go without any type of a response would have been seen as
like not defending God's honor. So you had to put him you
had to say you're in חרם *cherem* okay now so that wasn't
אפרושי מאיסורא *afroshe m'issura* but it was defending God's honor. So the
answer is when it comes to defending God's honor don't worry about
my honor mine the רבי'ס *Rebbe's* honor you do what you need
to do to defend God's honor. One moment we'll start with Charlie
yes and
this חילול ה׳ *chillul Hashem* was an accidental violation of a rabbinic
prohibition so that's kind of an extension.
Right that's also true it's rabbinic right so the idea of God's
authority even in protecting rabbinic law is a good point right. I
think a better word than also than disrespect maybe disparaging or something
I don't know I'll have to come up with a better word.
He used a tree on שבת *Shabbos*. You're not allowed to use
trees on שבת *Shabbos*. He's such a menace. So so that's what
I look look look look you know God's honor is
I understand I understand you know the alley.
So so look there are some times that because of protecting societal
norms like the famous story of אחר *Acher* and רבי rebbe, מאיר
*Rabbi Meir* is אחר *Acher* was there riding a you know a
horse on שבת *Shabbos*.
And he was a רבי rebbe *rabbi*.
I understand I'm just saying that you know look I just say
we're not in a position to judge based on the type of
society and what its norms were certain things could have been seen
to be like it's really important to make a statement about this
or else people will just think you know that it's a free-for-all
and you can disregard. So that was their judgment call, right? You
could say that's an interesting question. Let's say you're the תלמיד and
it's your judgment call that כבוד שמים Kavod Shamayim has to be
defended, and it's my, the רבי's rebbe, judgment call that this is
not needed or maybe even counterproductive to do this type of a
thing, right? So I think that that's like a really good question,
okay, but that was his judgment. You, we're not there, I'm not
going to judge about his judgment, but I do think it's a
good question about let's say, you know, how can I say I
should act במקום רב bimkom rav if maybe actually another judgment is
called for? But I understand what's bothering you, right?
Right, exactly. So it's becoming or we have that in another place,
women of the wall, right?
They feel that what another person is doing is
sullying God's honor and that gives them the motivation to throw rocks,
to
endanger
lives.
Look, I think you raise an excellent point. The גמרא, Gemara you
know, very basically, what, you know, conceives of a pretty, you know,
strict society in which people are kept to keep by הלכה halacha,
norms as interpreted by the rabbinic authorities. You know, and the גמרא
Gemara understands that not only would you give somebody lashes for violating,
that you could actually beat somebody up because he refuses to sit
in a סוכה, Sukkah, you know? So, you know, how that plays
out in with our democratic, you know, sort of ideals is a
really important question. But you're absolute, but if your question is like
are there reason, are there things in the גמרא Gemara that could
lead to supporting that type of a, you know, sort of theocratic
way of thinking of society? Right, right, I understand, right, I understand.
Well, it is objective הלכה, halacha. but it's rabbinic. God's honor is
being insulted,
so I will damage this person.
Well, it's not a permanent damage, he just has to basically, you
know, do תשובה teshuva and then it's taken off. But yes, that
is true. I mean, that yes, how this sort of more theocratic
model of the גמרא, Gemara. you know, can be embraced in a
modern democratic society? Right, I do, you're absolutely, you're right, you are
right, yes. My mistake, we said before, you know, because back
then, just reading it this way,
if you were like
a real thing, and a real thing, and so it was your
יורה יורה, yoreh yoreh, they said that's another שיעור, shiur, right?
Yeah, another שיעור. shiur.
So for that, so it was literally sort of like caveat then,
right? It was not יורה יורה ידין ידין במקום רב yoreh yoreh
yadin yadin bimkom rav or something like that, apparently.
No, no, I don't want, I'm not going to discuss that. Okay,
do you have a question? No. Okay, fine. Let's go on. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this.
כל מקום יפה. Kol makom yafeh. אמר רבא: באתר דאסור וחייב מיתה.
Be'asar de'asur vechayav misa. Now since we've talked about punishment, at least
it's God punishing, we're going to talk about the consequences of פסקing
psak במקום רב. bimkom rav. If you פסק psak literally in his
presence, then it's not only forbidden but you're deserving of death, heavenly
death. שלא בפניו אסור ואין חייב מיתה. Shelo befanav asur ve'ein chayav
misa. Not in his presence but maybe same city or same country
depending on discussions before, you're still forbidden but you're not deserving of
death. Now the גמרא Gemara is going to challenge this, but
challenge the second statement. ושלא בפניו לא? Veshelo befanav lo? Not in
his presence, you're not
חייב מיתה? chayav misa? והתניא, Vehatanya, I'll show you that even not
in his presence you're חייב מיתה. chayav misa. רבי אליעזר אומר: Rabbi
Eliezer omer: לא מתו בני אהרן עד שהורו הלכה בפני משה רבינו.
Lo mesu Bnei Aharon ad shehoru halacha bifnei Moshe Rabbeinu. The בני
אהרן Bnei Aharon only died because they פסקed psak in the presence
of משה, Moshe, not because they brought an אש זרה eish zarah
but because it was a פסק psak that they did in terms
of assuming the authority. מאי דרש? Mai darash? How do they see
this idea that they were supposed to bring a fire? Because the
פסוק pasuk says ונתנו בני אהרן הכהן אש על המזבח Venasanu Bnei
Aharon hakohen eish al hamizbeach that they should put the fire on
the altar, right just in the beginning of צו. Tzav. אמרו: אף
על פי Amru af al pi, שאש יורדת מן השמים, even though
the heaven, the fire comes from heaven, which it did when the
משכן Mishkan was erected, מצוה להביא מן ההדיוט, Mitzva lehavi min hahedyot,
nevertheless we have to bring our own. So they פסקed psak. that
they need to bring their own fire. Of course תוספות Tosafot points
out it's a little problem because those פסוקים pesukim are talking about
the outer altar and here they were bringing the קטורת ketoret on
the inner altar and you know, anyway, but okay. But this is
understanding that what made it זרה zarah was the fact not that
it wasn't appropriate but that
they were doing it under their authority and not משה's Moshe authority.
So אמרו אף על פי, I'm sorry what? ותלמיד אחד היה לו
לרבי אליעזר. Vetalmid echad haya lo leRabbi Eliezer. So that shows that
they were חייב מיתה. chayav misa. Now that was actually and they
died, so you see חייב מיתה. chayav misa. Number one. Number two,
ותלמיד אחד היה לו לרבי אליעזר שהורה הלכה בפניו. Vetalmid echad haya
lo leRabbi Eliezer shehorah halacha befanav. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer had a
student that פסקed psak in his presence. אמר רבי אליעזר לאימא שלום,
Amar Rabbi Eliezer le'Ima Shalom, so אימא שלום Ima Shalom was רבי
אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer wife. So he said to אמא שלום אשתו, Ima
Shalom ishto, his wife, תמיה
אני אם יוציא זה שנתו, Tamiah ani im yotzi zeh shenaso, I'd
be astounded if this person lived out the year. ולא הוציא שנתו,
Velo hotzi shenaso, and he didn't live out the
year. אמרו לו, Amru lo, so she said to him, נביא אתה,
Navi ata, you must be a prophet. אמר לה, Amar lah, he
said to her, לא נביא אנכי ולא בן נביא אנכי, Lo Navi
anochi velo ben Navi anochi, I'm not a prophet nor the son
of a prophet. אלא כך מקובלני, Ela kach mekubalni, I have a
tradition: כל המורה הלכה בפני רבו חייב מיתה. Kol hamoreh halacha bifnei
rabo chayav misa. Okay, one wonders if he would have been מוחל
mochel on his כבוד after the fact if that might have saved
this guy's life. Okay, משה? Moshe? Right, that's true. Right, אבל לגבי
משה, Aval legabei Moshe, we don't put משה Moshe in a position
of having known what
would have happened. ואמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, Ve'amar
Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan, and רבה בר בר חנה
Rabbah bar bar Chana says in the name of רבי יוחנן: Rabbi
Yochanan: אותו תלמיד יהודה בן גוריא שמו, Oso talmid Yehuda ben Guria
shemo, his So he was three פרסאות *parsaos* away. A פרסה *parsa*'s
four מיל *mil*, he was 12 מיל *mil*, 12 kilometers away. So
therefore you see that even שלא בפני רבו *shelo bifnei rabbo*, even
not physically in the presence, as long as maybe it's the same
city or the same country, you see that you're still חייב מיתה
mita *chayav mita*. So how could you distinguish between בפניו *bifanav* and
שלא בפניו *shelo bifanav*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, בפניו הוה
*bifanav havay*. So oh, no it was in his presence. What do
you mean? והרחוק ממנו שלש פרסאות קאמר *V'ha rachok mimenu shalosh parsaos
kamore*, it says he was three פרסאות *parsaos* away. So you see
even three פרסאות *parsaos* away you could be חייב מיתה *chayav mita*.
So no, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, ולטעמיך *u'letaymech*, according to you,
שמו ושם אביו למה *shmo v'shem avi lama*? Why do you have
to tell me his name was יהודה בן גוריא *Yehuda ben Gorya*,
who cares what his name was? אלא *Ela*, so what's the reason
of giving that detail? שלא תאמר משל היה *Shelo tomar mashal haya*,
you shouldn't say, oh this is just a משל *mashal*, it never
really happened, it's just like a lesson. No, it's a real story.
Now, so therefore what? And therefore the שלש פרסאות *shalosh parsaos* did
not mean that he פסק *paskened* three פרסאות *parsaos* away, it means
he lived three פרסאות *parsaos* away. So the point is, so who
needs that? That's a trivial biographical detail. No, we're giving trivial biographical
details because we want to make it clear that this was a
real story. So although the simple sense of that story is that
this idea of חייב מיתה *chayav mita* even if you're not physically
in the presence, the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* tones it down and says
the חייב מיתה *chayav mita*'s only if you are actually in the
presence. Yes.
And at the end of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer*'s life,
as he himself was put into חרם *cherem*,
right, right,
in the humiliation, right,
but that's not for פסק *paskening* what they did to him.
Right. Well he kind of caused the death.
Yeah, it's interesting to see this as, oh it
was so important, this guy had to go.
That's a good point, right, the רבי rebbe, אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* was
a רבי rebbe, *Rabbi*. That's a good point, right. I wouldn't say
because he was put in חרם *cherem*, I would say that story
of him being put in חרם *cherem* is his rigidity and his
inability like, and his inability
to be, right, to sort of accept the authority of his
חבריו *chaveirei*. So that's a good point, that he was so rigid
on not sort of on his own authority, and that in the
end ended with his own dying in disgrace. That is a very
good point. That is a very good point. Question, yes. I would
also say by the way, and I want to get back to
this point back in a minute, that the other interesting thing about
רבי Rebbe אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* and part of that whole story about
him, you know, dying and not reversing himself or whatever, is that
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says that רבי Rebbe אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* never
said anything he didn't hear from his רב *rav*. So according to
him, you know, there were these two schools of תורה Torah. שבעל
פה *Torah she-ba'al peh*. One was much more about just what you
receive you pass down, and the other was much more about the
human creativity. And he was very, very much from the what you
receive you pass down school. And therefore he couldn't accept anybody else's
opinion because he knew the truth, he had it straight from סיני
*Sinai*. If we all come up with our own ideas, you could
be open to other people's opinions and you know yours is not
absolutely true. But if you have a straight tradition, I obviously have
the right tradition, you have the wrong one. So anyway, that was
רבי rebbe אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*. So you also understand that that type
of an approach to תורה Torah, שבעל פה *Torah she-ba'al peh* emphasizes
much more the idea of כבוד הרב *kevod harav*, because you know,
as opposed to what we were talking before about the nature of
תורה Torah. שבעל פה *Torah she-ba'al peh* that everybody argues and has
their own opinion and so on, but that very much is about
authority of coming from on high and coming from previous generations and
so on. So that is actually also very consistent with this emphasis
on כבוד הרב *kevod harav*, yes.
This שלא תאמר משל היה *shelo tomar
mashal haya*, that's not something we see much in אגדתא *Aggadeta*.
Right, which is an interesting line which indicates that sometimes maybe it
is just a משל *mashal*, which sometimes we say when we're reading
it, but it's interesting for the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* to be sort
of itself aware of that possibility. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* continues. אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן כל המורה
הלכה halacha, לפני רבו ראוי להכישו נחש *Amar Rabbi Hiyya bar Abba
amar Rabbi Yochanan, kol hamoreh halacha lifnei rabbo ra'uy lehakhisho nachash*. Anybody
who פוסק *paskens* in front of the רבי *rebbe* is deserving for
a snake to bite him. Very similar to the idea of חייב
מיתה *chayav mita*. שנאמר Shene'emar, *Shene'emar*, for it says, ויען אליהוא בן
ברכאל הבוזי *V'ya'an Elihu ben Barkhel ha-Buzi*, so this is in of
course איוב *Iyov*, אליהוא בן ברכאל הבוזי *Elihu ben Barkhel ha-Buzi* responded,
ויאמר צעיר אני לימים ואתם ישישים על כן זחלתי *vayomar, tza'ir ani
l'yamim v'atem yeshishim, al ken zachalti*. I am a young one of
days, therefore I am, so the simple sense of the פסוק pasuk.
*pasuk* is I held back saying what I, you know, saying what
I should say in front of my elders. So so here plays
זחלתי *zachalti* is like זוחל *zochel*, a slithering, a snake. וכתיב U-chtiv
עם חמת זוחלי עפר *U'khtiv, im chamat zochelei afar*, with the poison
of those that slither in the dust. So you see that if
you are to speak in the front of your elders or פוסק
לפני רבו *pasken bifnei rabbo*, you're deserving of a snake. זעירי אמר
רבי חנינא נקרא חוטא chotei *Z'iri amar Rabbi Hanina, nikra chote*, you're
a sinner. Okay, now that's toning it down a little from חייב
מיתה *chayav mita*. Even להכישו נחש *lehakhisho nachash* is a little more
vague than חייב מיתה *chayav mita*, so you could sort of see
in these following statements a somewhat toning down of the earlier גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*. You're a sinner, שנאמר Shene'emar, בליבי צפנתי אמרתך *shene'emar, belibi
tzafanti imratecha*, I've held back your words in my heart, I didn't
express them in the presence of a greater authority, למען לא אחטא
לך *l'ma'an lo ekhta lach*, so that I not sin. רב המנונא
רמי *Rav Hamnuna rami*, רב המנונא *Rav Hamnuna* had a contradiction. כתיב
בליבי צפנתי אמרתך *Ktiv, belibi tzafanti imratecha*, I've held them in my
heart, so this is דוד David. *Dovid* speaking from תהלים *Tehillim*. וכתיב
u-chtiv בשרתי צדק בקהל רב *U'khtiv, bisarti tzedek b'kahal rav*, I have
spoken of your righteousness, meaning here's your Torah, in great congregation. So
did דוד David *Dovid* keep it to himself or did he teach?
לא קשיא כאן Kan בזמן שעירא היאירי היה קיים *Lo kashya, kan
bizman she-Ira ha-Yairi hayah kayyam*, one is when עירא היאירי Ira HaYairi,
*Ira ha-Yairi* was alive, interesting, sometimes. Sometimes, you know, who was דוד'ס
David's רבי in the rabbinic idea? Sometimes it's אחיתופל, Achitofel, or it's
מפיבשת. Mephiboshet. Anyway, here it's עירא היאירי, Ira HaYairi, we'll see in
a פסוק. pasuk Then, when he was alive, then, you know, he
couldn't פסקן in his presence and that even not in his presence
he's not allowed, you know. כאן or whatever, you know, כאן בזמן
שאין עירא היאירי קיים Kan be-zman she-ein Ira ha-Yairi kayam and the
other is when he's not
allowed. אמר רבי אבא בר זבדה, Amar Rabbi Abba bar Zavda, כל
הנותן מתנותיו לכהן אחד, kol ha-noten matnotav le-kohen echad, now that we're
talking about דוד'ס David's relationship to עירא היאירי, Ira HaYairi probably nobody
ever heard of him, but he actually is in a פסוק pasuk
we're about to quote. Anybody who gives his gifts, his כהונה kehunah
gifts, לכהן אחד le-kohen echad gives it all to one כהן, kohen,
מביא רעב לעולם, mevi ra'av la-olam, brings famine to the world because
you're not distributing it, you have all the other כהנים kohanim that
you're not giving it to, and that brings a more general famine
to the world, you know, a type of מידה כנגד מידה. midah
keneged midah. שנאמר, Shene'emar, the פסוק pasuk says, עירא היאירי היה כהן
לדוד. Ira ha-Yairi haya kohen le-David. עירא היאירי was a כהן kohen
for דוד. David, Now תוספות Tosafot says he wasn't literally a כהן
kohen because he's יאיר בן מנשה, Yair ben Menashe, but כהן kohen
literally in the sense of the פסוק pasuk means like a master,
you know, a רבי to דוד David which is how the גמרא
Gemara was reading it before, an officer. Not actually פשוט pashut it
means an officer of דוד, David one of דוד'ס David's officers. But
the גמרא before read it like a רבי of דוד David and
here it's reading it literally a כהן, kohen, he was דוד'ס David's
כהן. kohen. So לדוד הוא דהוי כהן ולכולי עלמא לא? Le-David hu
de-havei kohen u-le-kulei alma lo? He was a כהן kohen for דוד
David, and not for the rest of the world? אלא שמשגר לו
מתנותיו, Ella she-meshagger lo matnotav, דוד David gave him all דוד'ס all
of the gifts of דוד, which you'd imagine the king's תרומות ומעשרות
terumot u-ma'asrot you want to be on the top of that list,
okay, all went to this one guy. וכתיב בתריה U-chtiv batrei it
says afterwards ויהי רעב בימי דוד, Va-yehi ra'av bi-mei David, there was
a famine. Of course the famine related in the פסוקים pesukim related
to שאול, Shaul, but because of the juxtaposition we're understanding it to
be related to this. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, מורידינו אותו
מגדולתו, moridinu oto mi-gedulato, back to פסקן'ינג paskening in front of your
רבי, we went from מיתה to חוטא and now we're saying you
lose, you yourself lose some of your your authority which is a
type of מידה כנגד מידה. midah keneged midah. שנאמר, She-ne'emar, so again
we're toning it down a little bit. ויאמר אלעזר הכהן אל אנשי
הצבא, Vayomer Elazar ha-kohen el anshei ha-tzava, right when people came back
from the war and אלעזר הכהן Elazar HaKohen basically פסקן'ד paskened for
them. Said you know זה הדבר אשר צוה ה' את משה, zeh
ha-davar asher tziva Hashem et Moshe, את הזהב ואת הכסף, et ha-zahav
ve-et ha-kesef, you know and he told them what to do and
how to כשר kasher it and the whole thing. So אף על
גב דאמר להו, af al gav de-amar lehu, even though when he
פסקן'ד paskened he said to them, מאחי אבא צוה ואותי לא צוה,
me-achi abba tziva ve-oti lo tziva, he commanded my father's brother משה,
Moshe, not me. He said זה הדבר אשר צוה ה' את משה,
zeh ha-davar asher tziva Hashem et Moshe, he wasn't saying I know,
he said it was a command to משה. Moshe. אפילו הכי עניש,
Afilu hachi unash, he was punished because he shouldn't have been פסקן'ינג,
paskening, משה Moshe was around. דכתיב ולפני אלעזר הכהן יעמד, De-chtiv ve-lifnei
Elazar ha-kohen ya'amod, you should, you know when, but you know it's
taught about what יהושע'ס Yehoshua's going to do if he has a
question he should ask אלעזר הכהן. Elazar HaKohen. ולא אשכחן דאיצטריך יהושע
Ve-lo ashchachan de-itztarich Yehoshua and never in the whole book of יהושע
Yehoshua does he ever go to אלעזר הכהן Elazar HaKohen for a
שאלה. shayla So you see that even though he was deserving of
getting כבוד and authority and so on, it didn't play out that
way because he usurped authority when he was when משה Moshe was
around. So again it's this nice מידה כנגד מידה, midah keneged midah,
but it's also a little bit tamer, you know, and than the
more extreme statements before. Yes?
You said the רש"י Rashi over there say that because he בא
לכלכלה בא לקלטוסה? ba le-chalkas ba le-kaltos? Yeah, okay, multiple explanations. Come,
you know it's מדרש.
midrash. Yeah, yeah, yeah, fine. אמר רבי לוי, Amar Rabbi Levi, כל
המוסיף מילה לפני רבו, kol ha-mosif mila lifnei rabbei, now until now
we've been talking about פסקן'ינג. paskening. Now we're saying what's also פסקן'ינג
paskening but sort of framing it differently. Anybody who responds to a
word. Somebody comes up, you know, you know, and this happens I
gotta tell you sometimes it happens in the בית מדרש Beit Midrash
כולל kollel because people are like just so you know so into
it. Like, oh we've been learning, you know, we've been learning this
פרשה parsha or whatever and somebody walks into the בית מדרש Beit
Midrash and asks the רבי, oh I just, you know, did this
with my pot or whatever and somebody says, oh oh it's נותן
טעם לפגם notel ta'am lifgam et cetera you know and have to
answer the question. So anyway somebody who responds to a question that
was asked to the רבי, okay so in a way that's even
worse in a certain sense because it was like directed to the
רבי and this person is interjecting themselves. You can understand how people
get carried away. But you know interject and they're responding to a.
Well פסקן'ינג paskening or just responding? Well it's responding in a פסק.
Okay anyway the scenario I gave was it was asked to the
רבי, I admit that isn't explicitly the scenario in the גמרא. כל
המוסיף מילה לפני רבו Kol ha-mosif mila lifnei rabbei it's in the
presence of the רבי, but anyway the same point you respond to
a שאלה shaila in the presence of your רבי, אזיל
לשאול בלא בנים, ozil li-she'ol be-lo banim, so in case you
thought we were getting a little bit more toned down, so now
this person goes into the netherworld without children. שנאמר, ויען יהושע בן
נון משרת משה מבחריו ויאמר אדני משה כלאם Va-yaan Yehoshua bin Nun
mesharet Moshe mi-bechurav vayomar adoni Moshe kela'eim about the people that were
פסקן'ינג, paskening, you know, that were going out and being מתנבא, mitnabbe,
now the irony of that is is that יהושע Yehoshua was coming
to defend the authority of משה. Moshe. They are assuming, you know,
prophecy in your presence. So he wanted to protect משה'ס Moshe's authority
but nevertheless he himself was in his zeal and exuberance, you know,
also encroaching on משה'ס Moshe's authority. Don't tell me how to פסקן
about these guys and what to do with them. וכתיב and we
and it says נון בנו יהושע בנו Nun beno Yehoshua beno in
the listing of יהושע'ס Yehoshua's children, you know, it says נון Nun
and then יהושע Yehoshua and then it stops. So we never find
that יהושע Yehoshua had any children. Wow, so that's pretty heavy, right?
ופליג U-pelig ופליגא דרבי אבא בר פפא. U-pliga de-Rabbi Abba bar Pappa.
This argues with Rabbi Abba bar Pappa, דאמר רבי אבא בר פפא
de-amar Rabbi Abba bar Pappa לא נענש יהושע אלא בשביל שביטל את
ישראל לילה אחת מפריה ורביה. lo ne'enash Yehoshua ela bishvil she-bitel et
Yisrael laila achat mi-pirya ve-rivya. The reason he didn't have children was
as the מהרש''א Maharsha says מידה כנגד מידה mida k'neged mida because
he prevented בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael from having engaged in procreation, meaning
being able for the men to be with their wives for one
night. What's the story? שנאמר, the פסוק pasuk says ויהי בהיות יהושע
ביריחו, vayehi bi-hyot Yehoshua bi-Yeriho, when יהושע Yehoshua was in יריחו Yeriho
וישא עיניו וירא vayisa einav vayar and he saw and you know
there's that person והנה איש עומד לנגדו וחרבו שלופה בידו ve-hinei ish
omed le-negdo ve-harbo shlufa be-yado and he said למי אתה הלנו אתה
אם לצרינו le-mi ata halanu ata im le-tzareinu and he said, you
know, אני שר צבא ה' עתה באתי, ani sar tzva Hashem ata
bati, you know, I am an angel from God. This is when
they were encamped around יריחו. Yeriho. So here the גמרא says וכתיב
ויאמר כי אני שר צבא ה' עתה באתי. vayomer ki ani sar
tzva Hashem ata bati. אמר לו, Amar lo, so what was this
whole encounter about? So the angel said to him, אמש, emesh, last
night before it got dark, meaning yesterday, ביטלתם תמיד של בין הערביים,
bitaltem tamid shel bein ha-arbayim, you didn't bring the afternoon sacrifice. So
תוספות, Tosafot you know, people say where'd he get that from? How
does the גמרא know that? But so I'll tell you in a
minute what an answer תוספות Tosafot has. ועכשיו Ve-achshav and now, now
that everybody is spending time sort of in you know besieging the
city, ביטלתם תלמוד תורה, bitaltem Talmud Torah, you're not learning תורה. Torah
You're not—the people aren't going at war at night, so what are
you doing? You should be sitting and learning here when you're surrounding
יריחו. Yeriho. So תוספות Tosafot says how do you know any of
this, right? So תוספות Tosafot says, it's a—תוספות—I Tosafot mean again, it's—תוספות
Tosafot speculates—it's a play on words because he says, תוספות Tosafot, says
he says הלנו אתה אם לצרינו. halanu ata im le-tzareinu. So הלנו
halanu is תורה ציווה לנו משה Torah tziva lanu Moshe and לצרינו
le-tzareinu is that the, you know, the sacrifice, you know, in the
sense of the sacrifice is על הצר הצורר אתכם al ha-tzar ha-tzorer
etchem and to protect us from צרות tzarot and so on. So
it's a little bit of a stretch. But anyway, why are you
here? Are you here because of—we didn't bring the קרבנות korbanot or
because of the תלמוד תורה? Talmud Torah? על איזה מהן באת, al
eizeh me-hen bata, which one are you here for? Which one is
the worst one? אמר לו עתה באתי, amar lo ata bati, I've
come now. I've come because you haven't been doing תלמוד תורה. Talmud
Torah. מיד וילן יהושע בלילה ההוא בתוך העמק. Miyad vayalen Yehoshua ba-laila
ha-hu be-toch ha-emek. So that's actually not then, that's actually a later
battle, but it says he slept in the valley. Actually it's וילך
בתוך העמק, vayelech be-toch ha-emek, not וילן. vayalen. It's a combination of
two פסוקים. psukim. Anyway, ואמר רבי יוחנן ve-amar Rabbi Yochanan מלמד שהלך—notice
melamed she-halach שהלך she-halach because some versions are שלן בעומקה של הלכה,
she-lan be-omka shel halacha, he slept in the depths of הלכה. halacha,
And here it's שהלך she-halach because the real פסוק pasuk is וילך
יהושע. vayelech Yehoshua. I actually read it וילן, vayalen, but it's written
here וילך. vayelech. What difference does it have? וילך Vayelech or וילן?
vayalen? Anyway, doesn't matter. Some versions have וילן, vayalen, some have וילך.
vayelech. Anyway, מלמד שהלך בעומקה של הלכה. melamed she-halach be-omka shel halacha.
He went in the depths, so next time he was at a
battle site at night, he spent the night learning תורה, Torah. learning
הלכה, halacha okay? Because he learned his lesson. Okay, now that's all
very nice. What does it have to do with being—the—ביטל אותם bitel
otam from פרו ורבו? pru u-revu? That's ביטל אותם bitel otam from
תלמוד תורה. Talmud Torah. So most of the times when this מדרש
midrash is brought, it's all about the תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah point.
But here we are trying to make—give another explanation why יהושע Yehoshua
was childless. So what we're going to do is we're going to
piggyback on this דרשה drasha which elsewhere just ends right here and
is all about תלמוד תורה. Talmud Torah. We're going to say oh,
and by the way, there's also the problem that he stopped them
from פרו ורבו. pru u-revu. Where is that? So it's—ואמר רבי יוחנן—oh
ve-amar Rabbi Yochanan so it says, and so now the גמרא now
adds this line to this דרש: drash: דגמירי de-gmiri and we have
a tradition דכל זמן שארון ושכינה שרויים שלא במקומם, de-chol zman she-aron
u-shchina shruyim shelo bi-mkomam, that as long as the ארון aron and
the שכינה shchina are not in their right place, because here they
were, they were encamped around—actually they took the ארון aron against יריחו,
Yeriho, they took it to battle, אסורים בתשמיש המיטה, asurim be-tashmish ha-mita,
they could not have—they could not have sex. Now, so if that's—if—if—that
doesn't make sense. Like, the whole thing is that he wasn't learning
תורה. I mean, if they have to go to war and you're
supposed to take the ארון aron with you to war, so what
was he doing wrong? So if he was learning תורה that would
have made up for it? I mean, you know, what's going on
here? So that's why this last line is really stapled on at
the end and the real דרשה drasha here is about the תורה.
If to make sense of what the גמרא is talking about here,
you would have to say, because תוספות has a whole discussion here
about—he says what are you talking about? They're always taking the ארון
aron to war and like with דוד and אוריה Uriah and we
don't see any sense that you're not allowed to have sex when
the ארון aron is at war, is out. So תוספות says in
a very important תוספות, he basically says that there were two ארונות
aronot because there's the wood ארון aron that משה Moshe made after
he came down from הר סיני Har Sinai when he broke the
לוחות luchot and he put it in, and then there's the gold
inlaid one that they made for the משכן. mishkan. And he actually
says that the one they would normally take to war would be
the wood one with the broken לוחות, luchot, and the gold one
with the whole לוחות luchot would remain in the משכן. mishkan. And
then you would be allowed to have sex. But a few times
they actually did the wrong thing and they took the gold ארון
aron into war, like the time that it also got captured by
the פלשתים Plishtim and so on, and that was when it was
אסור בתשמיש המיטה. asur be-tashmish ha-mita. So, okay, so that's—so it finally
relates to the previous story. You could say יהושע's Yehoshua sin was
he took the wrong ארון aron into war and it made them
אסור בתשמיש המיטה. asur be-tashmish ha-mita. But again, it's really not related.
It's really two different מדרשים midrashim that are stapled together. The other
interesting thing I will mention, though, is—is this is an important גמרא.
Other similar ones you might remember that there's a גמרא about עלי's...
Eli children, and you know, and it says וישכבו את הנשים v'yishkevu
et hanashim and they slept with the women and the גמרא says
literally slept? So it says no no no what it means is
they postponed bringing their קרבנות korbanot so that they couldn't be back
with their husbands that night and it's כאילו שכבו עמהם ki'ilu shachvu
imachem and you know מענה me'aneh etc. That is a very important
גמרא that we teach that and this or whatever that whole ethos
about you know you get a שאלה about הלכות נדה Hilchos Niddah
about the need you know to sort of treat those שאלות shaylot
very seriously and you can't postpone and whatnot and also you know
if it's possible for husband and wife to be together you know
that you have to make sure that that's that's able to happen
and that you know so either you're delaying or you're being overly
מחמיר machmir and so on when it's not appropriate הלכה, halacha these
types of גמרות Gemarot and אגדתות Aggadatas are important very express a
very important ethos. Yes, according to the first opinion that it was
because יהושע בן נון Yehoshua bin Nun was if you will מורה
הלכה moreh halacha מורה הלכה moreh halacha right so that seems to
take it more as an absolute standard and not that it's the
rabbi we'll be מוחל mohal on because משה Moshe משה Moshe wasn't
מוחל mohal on it. No no no משה Moshe says מי יתן
כל עם נביאים Mi yiten kol am Neviim yes he says משה
Moshe was very pleased with it. No I completely disagree. משה Moshe
was completely upset that יהושע Yehoshua took it upon himself to פסקן
and משה Moshe actually had a different approach than יהושע's Yehoshua approach.
יהושע Yehoshua משה Moshe was not מוחל mohal on the fact he
was מוחל mohal on what they did on what you know he
was not מוחל mohal on יהושע. Yehoshua. He was מוחל mohal on
the act that יהושע's Yehoshua getting upset about. Okay, so now the
גמרא continues. אמר שמואל בר עינא משמיא דרב Amar Shmuel Bar Ina
Mishmei D'Rav גדול תלמוד תורה יותר מהקרבת תמידין. Gadol Talmud Torah yoter
me'hakravat temidin. Now that we're talking about יהושע Yehoshua the whole thing
now we get back to what the דרשה drasha normally is without
when it doesn't have that whole insertion about פרו ורבו pru u'revu
which was inserted here but it was really about the תלמוד תורה.
Talmud Torah. So you see תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah is more important
than bringing קרבנות. korbanot. דאמרי ליה אתא בתי. De'amreleh ata bati. Now
I came. I came because of the תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah not
because of the קרבנות. korbanot. Which by the way okay it's a
nice throwaway line fine but also you have to appreciate you're talking
now in a rabbinical culture where תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah is the
central religious experience when it used to be the central religious experience
was the מקדש Mikdash and the bringing of קרבנות. korbanot. We're actually
saying don't worry תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah is more important than קרבנות
תמיד. korbanot tamid. דאמרי ליה אתא בתי. De'amreleh ata bati. אמר רב
הונא אמר רב Amar Rav Huna Amar Rav כל הישן בכילה שאיש
ואשתו שרויים בה. Kol hayashan bekila she'ish v'ishto shruyin bah. So now
that we're talking about also this issue about getting between husband and
wife we're going to continue on that theme for a minute. Anybody
that dwells in a like in a tent essentially like a room
that a husband and wife are dwelling in עליו הכתוב אומר Alav
hakatuve omer regarding him the פסוק pasuk says, meaning you're sleeping in
you're sharing a room with a husband and wife not the same
bed but you're sharing a room. By him the פסוק pasuk says
נשי עמי תגרשון מבית תענוגיה. N'shei ami t'gareshun mibeit ta'anugeha. The wives
of my nation you have you know driven out from the house
of their pleasure meaning that you have basically caused husband and wife
to separate. You are not allowing them to be intimate tonight because
you've chosen to sleep in this room. So אה ואמר רב יוסף
Ah v'amar Rav Yosef ואפילו באשה נדה. Va'afilu b'ishah niddah. Even if
she's a נדה niddah which is powerful means just the idea that
your presence interferes with the intimacy of husband and wife not just
them having to be not just the physical intimacy not just the
sex but the emotional intimacy and the privacy of husband and wife
you know deserving of this פסוק as if you're divorcing husband and
wife driving them apart from one another. רבא אמר Rava Amar אם
אשה נדה היא תבא עליו ברכה. Im ishah niddah hee tavo alav
bracha. רבא had a different perspective. Wife's a נדה? niddah? Great sleep
there so keep them from having sex. So אמר so so ולאו
היא דאטו אידי מאן נטרה. v'lav hi d'atu idi man natra. So
who is who you know for the other 364 days in the
year what's keeping them not having hopefully not that many times but
anyway all the other times who's keeping them apart obviously the whole
point is that we trust them to keep הלכות נדה. Hilchos Niddah.
So don't be overly פרום frum at the quite the opposite you
have to respect their intimacy even when she even when they're not
able to be physically together. Okay. So now before we go on
we're about to go on to actually getting finally back to our
הלכות about the חצר chatzer and the מבוי mavoy and so on
I just did want to say one other very important thing from
the שלחן ערוך about פוסקן במקום רב paskening b'makom rav because I
mentioned before the whole approach about רבי אליעזר about receiving from your
רבי as opposed to a more sort of open type of a
תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah and how that approach also very much underscores
the authority of the רב and you know feeds into that. So
the other big shift that happens as opposed to a move from
the more you know passing down versus human creativity is the actual
fact of how much everything gets written down because you know in
an oral culture the previous generations are the repositories for all of
the information. They are the libraries. And you know and you know
so you can spend 20 years you could be smarter than your
רבי and spend 20 years learning from him but he has been
around longer and might just have more knowledge and there's no books
to be had so you know ultimately that sort of sense of
authority also to a large degree relates to this question of an
or to some degree I should say tied into the sense of
an oral culture. So which is interesting because in the שלחן ערוך
you remember the גמרא seems to dismiss that as significant because it
mentioned מגילת תענית. Megillat Taanit. You know even with מגילת תענית... Megillat
Taanit... Since it doesn't matter and that's something written down. But anyway
the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch himself says: יש מי שכתב שכל הכתוב
בספרים מפסקי הגאונים יכול להורות בימי רבו. Yeish mi shekasav shekol hakasuv
besfarim mipiskei hageonim yachol lehoros bimei rabbo. Anything that's written in a
ספרים sfarim you can פסקן even if your רבי is around. Okay
so that's maybe just the idea that okay because it's not really
פסק it's already written down. Okay. רק לא יורה דבר מלבו ולא
ישמוך על הכתב ללמוד מלתא למלתא מעצמו. Rak lo yoreh davar milibo
velo yismach al haktav lilmos milsa lemilsa miatzmo. So that's more of
an issue of don't use your judgment that's real פסקנ'ן. paskening. But
communicating what's written in שולחן ערוך that's okay, you know what's written
in some earlier פוסקים. So that's maybe that's maybe less of an
idea of what I was talking about. That's just the idea right
that it doesn't appear a חידוש, chiddush, but that's more the idea
of how much are you פסקנ'ן paskening and using your judgment or
you're just relaying what already has been פסקנ'ד. But the other point
I was making about the difference of culture is expressed here in
a פתחי תשובה Pischei Teshuvah where he says like this. He says
it says you can't פסקן בפני רבו. He says so עיין שבות
יעקב שכתב דלכן אוי לכל מי שהגיע להוראה שלא יורה שום הוראה
בלתי עיון תחילה בספר. ayein Shevus Yaakov shekasav delachen oy lechol mi
shehigia lehoraah shelo yoreh shum horaah bilti iyun techilah basefer. So if
you can't פסקן במקום רבו then what it really means nowadays is
you can't פסקן without looking it up, without checking without checking the
ספרים. sfarim. Why? כי רבותינו הן הן הספרים אשר נתפשטו בקרב ישראל.
Ki raboseinu hein hein hasfarim asher nispashtu bekerev Yisrael. Okay. So he
actually says the whole relationship has shifted. Yes we learn from our
רביים rebbeim we learn skills we learn insight we learn a דרך
derech but ultimately we're learning from the ספרים. sfarim. Once we get
the skills and the דרך derech the learning you know for most
people comes primarily through the relationship with the ספרים. sfarim. So now
אל יורה במקום רבו al yoreh bimkom rabbo means don't be מורה
moreh without consulting the ספר. sefer. And the way that this is
actually you know what do you call it the way that this
is sometimes articulated is as that we learn מפי ספרים ולא מפי
סופרים. mipei sfarim velo mipei sofrim. So the whole the whole relationship
has changed in an interesting way so that raises really interesting questions
about this you know אל יורה במקום רבו. al yoreh bimkom rabbo.
You know I would say though another interesting question of course is
about this is so with these different parameters of what constitutes מקום
רבו. makom rabbo. Is it נראה לחידוש nireh lachiddush is it a
judgment issue is it not a judgment issue? You know there's debates
about what constitutes מקום רבו. makom rabbo. So if you're asked a
שאלה who gets to decide if it's you know if it constitutes
a problem of במקום רבו or not and is your deciding that
it constitutes it doesn't constitute is that itself a הוראה במקום רבו?
horaah bimkom rabbo? Because you're deciding that it's not considered מקום רבו
makom rabbo you get to פסקן that because I'm around. Anyway so
I just I just have to tell you I know a guy
that that in his contract in his for the synagogue a rabbi
it says that he gets to decide all הלכה questions and he
gets to decide what's a הלכה question. So how do you answer
that? All right. Except Rabbi I'm still a little confused. Let's go
back then when they gave you permission to be יורה יורה ידין
ידין yoreh yoreh yadin yadin so it's a bit...